all right
[Music]
most people could name four of the basic
tastes sweet sour salty and bitter the
rare foodie may be able to nail Umami
but what about the Forgotten flavor
sense spicy this seeming neglect it's
somewhat surprising given that hot
peppers are one of the world's most
widely used spices in fact as many as
one in four people on the planet
currently eat chilies on a daily basis
raising the question why is spicy food
so popular
why do Some Like It Hot enjoying what is
at first glance and irritating and
potentially painful mouth sensation
according to one popular suggestion it
is the Endorphin hit the the release of
the natural morphine-like painkiller
chemicals from your brain you hear this
a lot in the popular press but we still
don't have any convincing evidence to
support it another suggestion is that we
learned to use it for its anti-microbial
properties before the age of
refrigeration given that spicy food
tends to be preferred by cultures living
in warmer climates
and for that matter maybe it makes us
sweat and thereby ultimately helps cool
us down then again maybe it's just
because people just like the taste
preference for spicy foods does seem to
run in families based on twin studies
comparing the preferences of identical
to fraternal twins genetic factors May
account for up to half of the variation
similar to the heritability of sweet and
sour preferences
it may also be hormonal researchers in
France noted that particularly males
like spicy food and wondered if it was a
testosterone thing so they took a group
of more than a hundred men and gave them
plate of mashed potatoes and asked them
to Tobasco the potatoes to taste after
taking saliva samples to measure their
testosterone levels and what do you know
men who had higher testosterone added
more hot sauce that may help explain
this study that found a correlation
between Hot Chili Pepper consumption and
muscle strength in adult males as an
aside when I was looking at the
testosterone literature I've ran across
this study that showed young men
experience an acute decrease in blood
testosterone levels after chugging sugar
water or whey protein powder
12 to 18 year olds were randomized to a
few scoops of protein powder or about
two cans of soda worth of sugar and
within 20 minutes saw a significant drop
in testosterone levels compared to a
sugar-free protein-free control
this is consistent with lower
testosterone levels found in people on
high protein low carb diets
anyway what does the consumption of hot
spicy foods do to our lifespan well a
massive study of a half million men and
women in China found that those
regularly eating spicy foods had an
Associated 14 reduction in total
mortality meaning the risk of premature
death
that could translate into about an extra
year onto your lifespan if it is cause
and effect
those of you who follow my work know
that there are two main potential issues
with observational studies reverse
causality and confounding factors in
other words instead of spicy foods
leading to less disease may be disease
is leading to less spicy food with sick
people eating blander diets however the
apparent benefit remained even after
excluding sick folks or those who were
just about to croak and so reverse
causality doesn't seem to explain it
though hey people who eat spicy food
probably drink more and what do they
drink in China green tea so maybe that's
what's going on I mean it'd be nice to
to replicate this in a non-green tea
drinking country or even a country that
drinks terrible stuff like the United
States and yet same thing a 13 risk
reduction in premature death
and the protective Association remained
even after controlling for
Mexican-American ethnicity as I detailed
before they have a longevity Advantage
presumably because they eat so many
beans
same thing was found in Italy this time
a 23 percent lower all-cause mortality
that'd be like two extra years of life
the authors include that minor dietary
changes such as just adding chilies to
one's usual diet could be a valuable
measure for improving health
there have been four studies done
overall including this one in Iran that
all found the same thing significantly
lower risk of premature death in fact
blacker Chili Pepper consumption was
associated with about the same lifespan
extension as turmeric even at just like
a pinch a day and those who did both
seem to do even better which is
consistent with the ability of a black
pepper compound to boost the
bioavailability of the turmeric compound
curcumin I've got about 50 videos of my
turmeric is so good for you but why my
Chili Peppers extend your life
we'll find out next
[Music]